Boker Tov. Today's דף *daf* is כ"ט *Chaf Tet*. With this we
will finish the third פרק perek *perek* and enter into the fourth
פרק perek. *perek* of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*, the fourth
and final פרק perek, *perek*. We pick up at the bottom of
כ"ח עמוד amud ב' *Chaf Chet Amud Bet*, three lines from the
bottom. And we're in the middle of a discussion of a lot
of issues, very central issues in other areas of ש"ס *Shas* that
רבא Rava *Rava* has introduced really almost all of them. One was
the issue about מצוות mitzvot. לאו ליהנות ניתנו *mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu*,
whether deriving benefit of fulfilling a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* is considered a
violation of
things that you're not allowed to drive benefit from. You know, רש"י
Rashi, *Rashi* reads it as a broader theological statement about: is the
purpose of מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot* to make our lives better, is the
purpose of מצוות mitzvos. *mitzvot* to be a burden, an obligation, a
responsibility? But really that's not the focus. The focus is whether it
constitutes a technical issue of הנאה hana'ah? *hana'ah*. An interesting example would
be: you can't get הנאה *hana'ah* from a dead body. Can you
dissect a corpse in order to learn medical knowledge? And the answer
is yes, because that is not considered הנאה *hana'ah*, although you might
say it's like invaluable הנאה *hana'ah*, it's הנאה *hana'ah* people pay tens
of thousands of dollars for. But nevertheless, it's not a type of
a physical or monetary benefit. So that was one discussion of מצוות
mitzvos לאו ליהנות ניתנו *mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu*. Then we got into
another discussion of whether you need כונה *kavanah* to fulfill the מצוה
mitzvah, *mitzvah*, מצוות mitzvos. צריכות כונה *mitzvot tzerichot kavanah*. All of the
evidence in the משניות *Mishnayot* is that you do need כונה *kavanah*,
presumably כונה *kavanah* for the purpose that you'll acknowledge and are aware
that this is a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* act and you have כונה
*kavanah* to fulfill the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*. רבא Rava's *Rava* says you
don't need כונה *kavanah*. And he reinterprets all of that material to
say that we're talking about intent to do the act you're doing,
but not necessarily intent to think of it as a מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah* or to do the act or to fulfill the מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah*. And then we finally transitioned into a third point, which is
the issue of בל תוסיף bal tosif *bal tosif* and בל תגרע
*bal tigra*. If מצוות *mitzvot* do not require כונה *kavanah*, then it
should be easy to transgress בל תוסיף bal tosif *bal tosif* adding
to a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* because automatically something will be defined as
part of the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* and you will have expanded the
מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*, like sleeping in a סוכה Sukkah *sukkah* on שמיני
עצרת Shmini Atzeret, *Shemini Atzeret*. And until now the answer to that
has been that if it's not during the time of the מצוה
mitzvah. *mitzvah*, it doesn't count. And that led into a whole discussion
of what's considering to be the time of the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*.
Now we continue this with again רבא Rava *Rava* trying to reconcile:
so on the one hand mitzvot don't need כונה *kavanah*, on the
other hand making it that you're not always going to be over
on בל תוסיף *bal tosif*. So let's take a look, three lines
from the bottom. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*, רבא Rava *Rava* says,
לצאת לא בעי כונה *la'atzeis lo ba'ei kavanah*. Look, to fulfill your
obligation, if you do the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* act even without intent
to do a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*, the act intended, intentional, but the
naming of it, labeling of it as a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* is
not your intention. Okay, you fulfill the obligation, you did the act.
לעבור la'avor, בעי כונה *la'avor ba'ei kavanah*. But to transgress בל תוסיף
*bal tosif*, that you need intent. Because fundamentally, look, if I take
the לולב lulav *lulav* on סוכות Succos *Sukkot*, that self-defines itself as
the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of taking the לולב lulav *lulav*. Whether or
not I have the intent, taking a לולב lulav. *lulav* and an
אתרוג etrog *etrog* and a הדס *hadas* and an ערבה *aravah* on
סוכות Succos *Sukkot* is a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* act. But if I
go ahead and in my other hand I'm holding onto a pencil,
or let's say I even have a pencil in the hand that
I'm holding לולב lulav *lulav* and אתרוג *etrog*, what makes that part
of the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* act that I now is over on
בל תוסיף *bal tosif*? There's nothing that makes holding a pencil a
מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* act unless I say: I want to do this
as part of the taking of the לולב lulav, *lulav*. Now I'm
over on בל תוסיף *bal tosif*. But objectively, that is not a
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* act. So to make that part of the מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* act, you need כונה *kavanah*. Similarly, if I sleep in
a סוכה *sukkah* on שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret *Shemini Atzeret*, forget the
issue we discussed the other day about זמנו zmano *zmano* and לאו
זמנו zmano, *lo zmano*, what makes it that I've expanded the מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of סוכה *sukkah* from a seven-day מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* to
an eight-day מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*? Maybe I'm just sleeping outdoors because I
like the outdoors. So since there's nothing about that act that objectively
makes it the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* act, it's not סוכות *Sukkot*, if
I want to be over on בל תוסיף *bal tosif*—want to, if
I'm going to be over on בל תוסיף *bal tosif*—I have to
define it as a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* act to incorporate it into
the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. A very reasonable position. לצאת לא בעי כונה
*la'atzeis lo ba'ei kavanah*, but לעבור *la'avor*, something that's not a מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* act and you're going to incorporate and you're going to
be over on בל תוסיף *bal tosif*, בעי כונה *ba'ei kavanah*. That
would only happen if you had intent to make it part of
the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* act.
Like the כהן Kohen *Kohen* who added a fourth blessing.
So the כהן *Kohen* who added a fourth blessing, he says: I
want to now give them an additional blessing. So I'm intending to
have this as part of the blessing that I am giving the
people. Okay? So that would be an example
of כונה *kavanah*. But
the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
ask the case of the blood and the one application and four
applications that there clearly you're not trying to expand the מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah* and there's an issue of
בל תוסיף *bal tosif*.
Exactly, exactly, makes an enormous amount of
sense. So now the גמרא Gemara says ומתן דמים
דרבי יהושע דלאו עובר ולא בעי כוונה,
v'maten damin
d'Rabbi
Yehoshua d'lav ovar v'lo ba'i kavana,
how about the putting of the blood that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
says that that's a problem of of בל תוסיף and there's no
כוונה kavana there? And if that was an issue, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer could have answered back there's no כוונה. kavana. Now, by the
way, you could say that is exactly what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
answered back. You might remember yesterday רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says לא
נאמר בל תוסיף אלא כשהוא לעצמו. lo ne'emar bal tosif ela k'shehu
l'atzmo.
Remember that line? בל תוסיף was only a problem if you're doing
it by itself and expanding it. Here, the reason you're expanding it
is because it's mixed up with the other blood and you have
no choice but to do four. So that might actually be what
he meant. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara sees that as a significant
challenge, although this statement was a very logical position. אלא אמר רבא.
ela amar Rava. So רבא Rava is going to modify it even
further. לעבור לא בעי כוונה. la'avor lo ba'i kavana. Like I said,
to fulfill the obligation, you don't need intent. לעבור, not to transgress,
and the phrase I used a minute ago was supporting scaffolding, it
matters what the context is. בזמנו, bizmano, if you're expanding the מצוה
mitzvah. during the time of the מצוה, mitzvah לא בעי כוונה. lo
ba'i kavana. Then even without intent, something naturally gets incorporated into the
מצוה. mitzvah, So you did one and you made it four during
the actual performance of the מצוה. mitzvah You expanded what that you
expanded it even without intent. You've now expanded the מצוה. mitzvah, אבל
שלא בזמנו, aval shelo bizmano, not in its time, like sleeping in
a סוכה on שמיני עצרת, there, there's nothing that defines it as
part of the מצוה. mitzvah. So that בעי כוונה, ba'i kavana, you
would need intent. Okay, so זמנו zmano, can incorporate it and שלא
בזמנו, shelo bizmano, what you need to incorporate it is כוונה. kavana.
And that at least addresses some of the issues before, like the
issue about the ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, if there was כוונה, kavana,
the דם, dam, there wasn't כוונה, kavana, but that was זמנו, שמיני
עצרת is not זמנו, and no כוונה. kavana. Now, by the way,
that still does raise some questions, like, you know, really? So like
if I'm taking my לולב lulav and אתרוג and I've got like
my ring on my finger, so now it's בזמנו, bizmano, לא בעי
כוונה lo ba'i kavana because I've now taken five, you know, another
object? Or let's say, forget it, let's say I just take off
my glasses for a second and I'm holding my glasses as I'm
taking it, right? So לא בעי כוונה, lo ba'i kavana, you know,
am I being עובר? over? So it's still I think is an
interesting question of what כוונה kavana we mean. The same way before
we talked about כוונה kavana as כוונה kavana to do a מצוה,
mitzvah right? So here when we say לא בעי כוונה, lo ba'i
kavana, you don't need כוונה kavana to say like I am doing
this as an expanded מצוה. mitzvah, Like when you're doing the מתן
דמים, matan damin, you're not intending to expand the מצוה, mitzvah but
you're still like intending to do the act or aware that you're
doing the placing of blood in an expanded way even though it's
not for the sake of a מצוה. mitzvah So you know, if
I said I want to hold five objects in my hand, right?
That would incorporate it even if I wasn't doing it for the
sake of expanding the מצוה. mitzvah. So it's still a like an
interesting narrow line to walk, what that means לא בעי כוונה. lo
ba'i kavana. It doesn't mean everything automatically, I have no idea what
that is, it doesn't mean automatically everything is part of the מצוה,
mitzvah? it just means that, oh I think it's, anyway, it doesn't
mean everything is part of the מצוה, mitzvah it just means that,
it just means that the כוונה kavana to say I'm trying to
expand the מצוה, mitzvah I'm trying to make this part of the
מצוה act, a bigger מצוה act, that כוונה kavana you don't need.
That כוונה kavana you don't need if it is בזמנו. bizmano. But
again it doesn't mean that everything you're doing בזמנו bizmano
automatically becomes incorporated into the מצוה. Okay, there was a question? Yes.
Right. Yesterday we had the idea that כוונה kavana doesn't necessarily mean
כוונה kavana to do the מצוה, but כוונה kavana to do the
act, like when you said you had your glasses and you didn't
mean to hold your glasses in the מצוה act if you...
well I might have meant to hold my... right. That's exactly what
I'm trying to say. You know רבא's Rava כוונה kavana when he
says מצוות לא בעי כוונה, mitzvot lo ba'i kavana, that's exactly what
I'm trying to say. When רבא Rava says מצוות לא בעי כוונה,
mitzvot lo ba'i kavana, he means you don't need כוונה kavana to
be יוצא, yotze, right? But you do need כוונה kavana to do
the act. A similar לעבור בזמנו לא בעי כוונה, la'avor bizmano lo
ba'i kavana, meaning if you're doing it בזמנו, bizmano, you don't have
to intend to do this as a מצוה act. Okay, but you
still have to intend to do it in a certain way that
makes it incorporated into what you're doing, right? Exactly. So that's exactly
the point I'm getting at. Okay, fascinating issue of what would define
something a מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah when it's not a מעשה מצוה.
ma'aseh mitzvah. How much during the right time does it get incorporated
and how much if it's not the right time you need explicit
כוונה. kavana. Now the גמרא Gemara. continues. אמר רב זירא לשמעיה. amar
Rav Zeira l'shmaya. רב זירא Rav Zeira said to his
attendant, איכוון ותקע לי, ikaven u'tka li, have כוונה kavana when you're
blowing the שופר shofar and blow for me. Now what's being added
here in addition to the discussion of מצוות צריכות כוונה mitzvot tzrichot
kavana and presumably he's assuming that מצוות צריכות כוונה mitzvot tzrichot kavana
is that you need כוונה להוציא. kavana l'hotzi. If I am discharging
you of your obligation, it's not enough that I'm intending that this
blowing of a שופר shofar be a מצוה of blowing of a
שופר. shofar. In order for this blowing to connect to you and
for you to be יוצא, yotze, I have to intend to help
discharge this obligation for you. I have to have כוונה להוציא. kavanah
lehotzi. That was the phrase before, עד שיכוין שומע ומשמיע, ad sheyichavein
shomeia umashmia, but here specifically it's not just for my own blowing,
I have to make it a תקיעת שופר tkias shofar for me,
I have to have כוונה kavanah to be מוציא motzi you. Okay?
Like you know, you get the Kiddush, everyone's standing around, have כוונה
kavanah to be מוציא motzi me, right? Everybody says that, right? Why
don't you just hear and say Amen? Well, is it because we're
פוסק paskening מצוות צריכות כוונה? mitzvos tzrichos kavanah? But he has כוונה
kavanah to be doing Kiddush. No, but you assume that it doesn't
connect to me unless I say have כוונה kavanah to be מוציא
motzi me. Okay, and that's this סוגיא. sugya.
So the סוגיא sugya was looking at it from the outside...
oh, a גירסא, girsa, let's take a look. The גמרא'ס Gemara's going
to discuss it. Excellent. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלמא קסבר, alma
kasavar, so you see he's of the opinion, משמיע בעי כוונה, mashmia
bei kavanah, the one who causes it to be heard needs כוונה
kavanah and again specifically not סתם כוונה, stam kavanah, but כוונה kavanah
to be מוציא motzi somebody. מתיבי, meiseivei, I'll ask you on this,
היה עובר אחורי בית הכנסת או שהיה ביתו סמוך לבית הכנסת ושמע
קול שופר או קול מגילה, haya over achorei beis hachneses o shehaya
beiso samuch leveis hachneses veshama kol shofar o kol megillah, there you
go, David, you could have written the גמרא. Gemara So you happened
to have overheard the שופר shofar or the מגילה, megillah, אם כיוון
לבו יצא ואם לאו לא יצא. im kivein libo yatza veim lav
lo yatza. If you had intent, you fulfill the obligation, and if
not, you did not fulfill. So the גמרא Gemara says, דכיון לבו
מאי הוי? dekivein libo mai havei? Who cares that you had intent?
האי, hai, the other guy, לא קמכוין אדעתא דידיה. lo kamichavein adaata
dideih. He didn't have intent. He was just... he didn't realize you
were behind the שול shul in the neighboring house. The גמרא Gemara
says
no, האי לא קמכוין אדעתא דידיה. hai lo kamichavein adaata dideih. He
didn't have intent for you, for your intent. The גמרא Gemara says,
הכא בשליח ציבור עסקינן. hacha bishliach tzibbur askinan. No,
here we're talking about the guy who's doing it, I mean it
makes sense, it's in a בית כנסת, beis kneses, is the guy
who is the representative of the congregation, which doesn't necessarily mean that
the מקרי makri of the מגילה megillah has to be the guy
that davens שחרית shacharis or the בעל תוקע baal tokeia has to
be the בעל מוסף, baal musaf, but presumably it means that if
you're in the position to do it for the ציבור, tzibbur, right,
a שליח shliach of the ציבור, tzibbur, you are doing it for
the sake of the ציבור, tzibbur, דדעתיה אכולי עלמא. dedaateih achulei alma.
His intent is for anybody that hears, right? He doesn't think about
exactly how many people are here, which are the people, and he
doesn't even think so narrowly as everybody in שול. shul. He knows
he's doing it for other people, so he has a blanket intent
that anybody who needs to be יוצא yotze with this, I'm being
מוציא. motzi. All right?
So therefore that's why it works. תא שמע, ta shema, let's come
and try again. נתכוין שומע ולא נתכוין משמיע נתכוין משמיע ולא נתכוין
שומע לא יצא עד
שיכוין שומע ומשמיע. niskavein shomeia velo niskavein mashmia niskavein mashmia velo niskavein
shomeia lo yatza ad sheyichavein shomeia umashmia. ברייתא braisa we quoted yesterday,
you need the intent both of the listener and of the one
who makes the sound. קתני משמיע דומיא דשומע. katani mashmia dumya deshomeia.
So it describes the intent of the one blowing similar to the
intent of the one hearing. מה שומע שומע לעצמו, mah shomeia shomeia
le'atzmo, the same way the requisite intent for the hearer is just
to fulfill his own obligation, אף משמיע משמיע לעצמו, af mashmia mashmia
le'atzmo, so presumably the only requisite intent for the blower is to
do his obligation. Right, it doesn't distinguish between the intent. It says
you need intent for your מצוה, but I need intent to be
מוציא motzi you. No, it describes our intent equally, so presumably even
when I'm blowing it, my intent is just to be מוציא motzi
me, and even so that suffices, דקתני לא יצא. dekatani lo yatza.
And this is a little counterfactual, and it says that if you
don't have that intent, you're not יוצא, yotze, but the implication is
as soon as you intend to be יוצא, yotze, you're יוצא, yotze,
even if you don't have intent to be מוציא motzi somebody else.
So you understand the question? It speaks about the listener and the
blower having intent, and it describes it as the same type of
intent. It doesn't introduce this new idea that you need intent to
be מוציא motzi someone. That's a new type and a different type
of intent that's not being mentioned here. So the גמרא Gemara says
that's a pretty good proof. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנאי היא,
tannai hi, you know what? Good, you made a good point, but
it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. דתניא, detanya, we taught in one
ברייתא, braisa, שומע שומע לעצמו ומשמיע משמיע לפי דרכו. shomeia shomeia le'atzmo
umashmia mashmia lefi darko.
So another ברייתא braisa says the listener has to listen, only needs
to listen for himself. The one who's blowing has to somehow... we're
reading משמיע לפי דרכו mashmia lefi darko means not just for himself,
but in his normal way he's doing it that others hear, so
his intent has to be for the sake that others can hear
and that others can be יוצא. yotze. It's not so explicit there,
but we're sort of acknowledging that there is that debate. The other
ברייתא braisa didn't sound that way, but yes, you do have to...
we are saying there's another opinion that it's not enough to have
intent to be יוצא, yotze, you need intent to be מוציא motzi
someone. אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosi, said Rabbi Yosi, by the
way, just so you know the right English word to use, because
sometimes people say like have intent to fulfill my obligation for me.
I'm not fulfilling your obligation, I'm not a fulfiller, you're the fulfiller.
I'm like helping you discharge your obligation. That's the way I frame
it. Anyway, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבי
יוסי במה דברים אמורים בשליח ציבור אבל ביחיד לא יצא עד שי...
amar Rabbi Yosi bameh devarim amurim bishliach tzibbur aval beyachid lo yatza
ad she... I'm sorry, oh, I misread it. So no, לפי דרכו
lefi darko just means right, I'm sorry, I jumped ahead. So the
first משמיע לפי דרכו mashmia lefi darko just means normally you don't
have to have special intent. Okay, so the ברייתא braisa says if
you're blowing the שופר, shofar, you don't need special intent, you just
blow. אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosi, now Rabbi Yosi clarifies this.
במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, what does that mean? משמיע לפי
דרכו mashmia lefi darko just means normally you don't have to have
special intent. Okay, so the ברייתא braita says if you're blowing the
שופר, shofar, you don't need special intent, you just blow. אמר רבי
יוסי, Amar Rabi Yosi, now רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi clarifies this, במה
דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, what does it mean you don't need
special intent? בשליח ציבור, bishliach tzibur, if you are the שליח ציבור,
shliach tzibur, so your סתם stam intent works, you just do it
לפי דרכו, lefi darko, you do it without thinking anything special because
of course you're the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibur, you're doing it for
other people to be יוצא. yotze. אבל ביחיד, aval beyachid, but if
you're just an individual blowing the שופר, shofar, לא יצא עד שיתכוון
שומע ומשמיע, lo yatza ad sheyitkaven shomea umashmia, there you need the
special intent, not just of the one who listens, but the one
who blows, presumably meaning, and he needs to be blowing for your
sake. So while you're right the earlier ברייתא braita seemed to say
שומע ומשמיע shomea umashmia in the same breath, here it's clear by
making a distinction in רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi about the שליח ציבור
shliach tzibur and a normal person, that there's a special idea of
having כוונה להוציא kavana lehotzi you. So שליח ציבור shliach tzibur we
assume it's the blanket כוונה, kavana, but a normal private individual, if
you want to be יוצא yotze through them, they have to have
כוונה להוציא kavana lehotzi you.
Now is this also applicable let's say to the שבת Shabbat table
where you've got six discrete people there around the table, you should
have them specifically...
Yeah, but overall, somebody says, "Oh, oh, I don't know, did you
have me in mind, like I was in the other room," or
whatever, I'll say, "I have in mind anybody who hears me and
wants to be יוצא." yotze. That's just like my blanket כוונה, kavana,
but often you're right, people don't think about that. They're thinking about
the people in front of them, they weren't thinking about somebody that
was behind the door and that they didn't realize was there. So
this is the added idea that you need כוונה להוציא. kavana lehotzi.
Now here's an interesting thought experiment. Do, can you פסקן pasken both
like רבא that מצוות אינן צריכות כוונה mitzvot einan tzerichot kavana and
that you need כוונה להוציא? kavana lehotzi? Right, because the גמרא Gemara
had a whole long discussion of רבא מצוות אינן צריכות כוונה, mitzvot
einan tzerichot kavana, which was the way the whole previous עמוד amud
ended, and now we're having a whole discussion that if you want
to fulfill your obligation through hear somebody תקיעת שופר, tkiat shofar, he
needs כוונה kavana to be מוציא motzi you. So presumably the answer
is it's possible to hold both of those things. If I'm doing
the מצווה mitzvah object, I'm taking לולב without any special כוונה, kavana,
I still physically took the לולב. Check, I get credit. If I
blew the שופר shofar without כוונה kavana to do a מצווה mitzvah
but I was realizing I was making sound, I did the act,
check, I get credit. But here the problem is you're not doing
the act. This other guy is doing the act. What makes it
your act? So there, in order to make it your act, he
has to have intent to connect that act to you. And you
might have to have intent to connect to him too, right? So
that becomes an issue about, now again, maybe that's a little different
if you're the hearer because we're focusing on the one that's making
it heard. And the whole ברייתא braita before about walking behind a
בית כנסת beit knesset did not, we did not discuss that that
was different because you were hearing it as opposed to doing it.
But certainly, to create that link, I might need special intent to
be מוציא motzi you. So it's a different question. One is you're
doing the act, you did the physical act,
does it count if you didn't have special כוונה? kavana? And רבא
says yes. The other question is you didn't do the physical act.
Somebody else did it. What allows that to count as yours? That
might require that that person is having כוונה להוציא kavana lehotzi you,
without that, it's just random sound, it does not become your act.
And now the question is how we פסק. pasken. We certainly פסק
pasken that if you want to be מוציא motzi somebody you need
כוונה להוציא kavana lehotzi them. How about if you're doing the מצווה,
mitzvah, do we say מצוות צריכות כוונה mitzvot tzerichot kavana or not?
It's a major debate in the ראשונים rishonim and the פוסקים. poskim.
We generally tend to פסקן pasken that for דאורייתאs de'oraita we assume
it needs כוונה kavana and for דרבנןs derabanan we assume that בדיעבד
bedi'avad they don't, although again, it's an issue of major debate. Yes,
Joe?
What I don't remember, I'm not holding exactly, like what are the
parameters, the limits, for example, okay, you'll be מוציא motzi me in
קריאת מגילה kriat megillah or the שופר. shofar. You'll be מוציא motzi
me you're going to shake your לולב and be מוציא... motzi...
No. So basically the idea of being able to be מוציא motzi
somebody and we're going to revisit this again a little bit at
the end is limited to auditory מצוות. So ברכות, brachot, and מקרא
מגילה, mikra megillah, תקיעת
שופר, tkiat shofar, so... Well, קריאת התורה kriat hatorah is a ציבור
tzibur sort of type of a of a ritual, it's not it's
not an individual חיוב. chiyuv. You know, the question becomes things like
קריאת שמע kriat shema or תפילה, tefilah, even in some of those
more auditory מצוות that have this auditory component, they might be might
require that it sort of be coming from you, initiated from you,
rather than initiate from the outside. There's ירושלמי Yerushalmi about that. But
the basic discussion of being מוציא motzi somebody are things that are
basically auditory and by it's sort of if the tree falls in
a forest and no one hears it does it make a sound?
You know, listening is a part of that creating of that sound,
that there's a receiver to that sound, and becomes connects to that
act of the
sounds or of the words that were produced. So that's the principle
of שומע כעונה, shomea ke'oneh, the principle, so it's really limited to
auditory things. I do want to say though conceptually it is different
to say it by something that's about words as opposed to something
that's about like something that's about an action that is auditory but
it involves physical objects. So for example, it's one thing to say
that if you say a ברכה bracha and I heard the ברכה,
bracha, it's like I said the ברכה. bracha. Those were the words,
I heard them, I assented to them, so I connect to those
words, it's like I said those words. But if you say hear
I heard those sounds, it's one thing to say... I say I
connect to the sounds, but is it like I blew the שופר,
shofar, like I put a שופר shofar to my lips and blew
a שופר shofar because I heard those sounds? So as we've been
discussing by שופר shofar there's a question whether it's hearing or blowing.
One argument that it's about hearing and not blowing is it's hard
to understand how listening to ta ta ta ta ta ta ta
ta ta makes it like I took a ram's horn and put
it to my lips. But we have something like that by reading
the מגילה. Megillah. Right, the idea of reading the מגילה Megillah is
not to say the words of the מגילה, Megillah, it's to read,
to have a physical מגילה Megillah in front of you and to
read the words off of the scroll. So you heard those words,
so it's like you said ויהי בימי אחשורוש, Vayehi Bimei Achashverosh, but
is it like you read ויהי בימי אחשורוש Vayehi Bimei Achashverosh off
of a scroll? So it is a little bit unclear, you know,
how they all get put in the same category, but the basic
discussion of שומע כעונה Shomeia Keoneh is by things that are auditory.
Yes, but that's what I'm saying, that normally שומע כעונה Shomeia Keoneh
starts with things that don't involve physical objects, starts with things that
are just about words, about תפילה Tefillah and ברכות. Brachot. We then
wind up, right, talking about קריאת מגילה Krias Megillah and תקיעת שופר,
Tekias Shofar, but the common denominator is they're all auditory.
Exact, is there a מחלוקת machloket in the רן Ran about what
the wording of the ברכה bracha is for reading the מגילה? Megillah?
I,
it might be exactly to this.
No no no, the מגילה, Megilla, the גמרא Gemara is clear, it's
about קריאת מגילה, Krias Megillah, the issue is about
תקיעת שופר Tekias Shofar whether it's about תקיעה Tekiah or שמיעה. Shmiah.
Okay, let's take a look now. Next משנה. mishnah. Now, והיה כאשר
ירים משה, Vehaya Kaasher Yarim Moshe, now the משנה mishnah ends this
פרק perek, with a little אגדתא aggadeta based on this idea of
כוונה. kavanah. And although we had a discussion earlier whether כוונה kavanah
means כוונה kavanah to do the מצוה or כוונה kavanah to do
the act, it's clear that this משנה, mishnah, at least aggadically, but
probably also because it was the פשט pshat of the previous משנה,
mishnah, is assuming that the key is כוונה kavanah to do the
מצוה, not to סתם stam to realize you're making sounds rather than
cleaning out your שופר. shofar. So let's take a look. והיה כאשר
ירים משה ידו וגבר ישראל וכאשר יניח ידו וגבר עמלק. Vehaya Kaasher
Yarim Moshe Yado Vegavar Yisrael Vechaasher Yaniach Yado Vegavar Amalek.
Okay, so when he lifted up his hand, ישראל Yisrael was victorious.
וכי ידיו של משה עושות מלחמה או שוברות מלחמה? Vechi yadav shel
Moshe osos milchamah o shores milchamah?
Do the hands of משה, Moshe, do is that what made the
war or is that what destroyed the war? Is that what what
effect did his hands have? What type of magic was this? אלא,
Ella, there's a פרחי Pirchei song based on this משנה, mishnah, right?
Does anybody know that? All right. אלא לומר לך, Ella Lomar Lecha,
to tell you, כל זמן שהיו ישראל מסתכלין כלפי מעלה ומשעבדין את
לבם לאביהם שבשמים, kol zman shehayu Yisrael mistaklin klapei maalah umeshabdin es
libam la'avihem shebashamayim, that when they would look and see משה's Moshe
uplifted hands, they'd look towards the heavens and they'd think about God
and they'd subjugate themselves to God, so therefore שהיו מתגברין shehayu misgabrin
and therefore God would help them win and be victorious. ואם לאו,
Ve'im lav, and if they would not, you know, be looking towards
God, היו נופלין, hayu noflin, they would fall in battle. כיוצא בדבר
אתה אומר, Keyotzei vadavar atah omer, similarly you say another thing that
looks to be magical. עשה לך שרף ושים אתו על נס, Ase
l'cha saraf vesim oto al nes, make for you a fiery serpent
and put it on a banner.
והיה כל הנשוך
וראה אתו וחי, Vhayah kol hanashuch vera'ah oso vachai, anybody who's bitten
would look at it and live. וכי נחש ממית או נחש מחיה?
Vechi nachash meimis o nachash michayeh? Can the snake bring death or
the snake bring life? Pretty funny, the snake did bring death into
the world. You wonder if they are alluding to that. Anyway, אלא
בזמן שישראל מסתכלין כלפי מעלה ומשעבדין את לבם לאביהם שבשמים, Ella bizman
sheYisrael mistaklin klapei maalah umeshabdin es libam la'avihem shebashamayim, when they look
up to the banner and they see they think about God, היו
מתרפאין, hayu misrap'in, they'd be healed. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, היו נימוקים,
hayu nimokin, and if not, they would waste away. Now obviously this
is doing two things. Number one is it is talking about the
religious significance, not the halachic significance, the religious significance of כוונה. kavanah.
Before we described that you need כוונה kavanah if you're walking by
the שול shul to be יוצא, yotzei, and here we're making a
broader point, that you know, the there's an important religious impact that
is affected by an act when it's accompanied by כוונה, kavanah, then
it's not just some technical act, then the act actually connects you
to God and takes on religious significance. Okay, so number one כוונה
kavanah really matters from a religious plane beyond its meaning in terms
of a halachic consideration. The other thing of course that it's doing
is taking things which are like somewhat, you know, magical and do
somewhat sort of seem if anything, you know, could be read the
opposite, could be read like yes, sometimes there's just certain magic things
that you do, technical things that you do and poof, it works,
right? You lift up your hands, you look at a snake, you
look at whatever, you know, so it's so
and they're reframing it that that's not what it was really about.
It was really about this is a means of getting you, you
know, to think about God. So sort of de-magicalizing, I don't know,
you know, these stories which a might have been the opposite message
of כוונה kavanah and even forgetting the כוונה kavanah discussion, could have
been a harmful religious message. Like you know, these are troubling stories
that seems like there's just these types of things that somehow magically
have this type of an impact, you know, and the whole part
of the תורה Torah is just to sort of wipe out that
whole area of like magic and necromancy and incantation and it's all
about, you know, you and God and מצוות. So they this is
how therefore these it's being sort of these are being reframed. Okay,
whether it's פשט pshat in the פסוקים psukim is a much bigger
question. Okay, so now it goes on, there's no גמרא Gemara on
that by the way. Okay, so now we get back to הלכה.
halacha. All right, so it's like this. Oh, that's true. חרש שוטה
וקטן אין מוציאין את הרבים ידי חובתן. Cheresh, Shote, V'Katan ein motzi'in
es harabim yedei chovasan. A deaf-mute,
a שוטה, shote, which is somebody that is like not of their
right mind, somebody who's, you know, it's more like somebody like
insane or, you know, doesn't really understand reality as much as, well,
maybe insane is the wrong term also. But anyway, but somebody that
doesn't,
you know, isn't like linked to to
an anchoring in reality. And there's a whole discussion which we'll get
to in another מסכת masechet about how to define that. והקטן V'hakatan
and a minor, all these people are not considered to be בר
דעת. bar da'as. Of course חרש cheresh is a big issue, you
know, which has a whole modern history to it when sign language
for the deaf, etc., then the whole category of חרש cheresh got
sort of reconsidered. But anyway, these were the three that in the
time of that were assumed to be not בני דעת, bnei da'as,
קטן katan from a formalist perspective, and אין מוציאין את הרבים ידי
חובתן. ein motzi'in es harabim yedei chovasan. They cannot discharge the masses
their obligations. They cannot be the ones to blow שופר. shofar. זה
הכלל, Ze haklal, this is the principle: כל שאינו מחויב בדבר, kol
she'eino mechuyav badavar, if you're not obligated, אינו מוציא את הרבים ידי
חובתן, eino motzi es harabim yedei chovasan, you cannot be the one
to have the ציבור tzibur discharge its obligation. So this frames the
idea of blowing the שופר shofar for someone, like we described earlier,
as being מוציא motzi that person. And that led to the earlier
discussion about כוונה. kavannah. Let's take a look.
I think it's striking that women are not in that list.
Yes, it is striking, and the גמרא Gemara is going to sort
of quote a ברייתא braisa and sort of assume that, but it
is quite fascinating that it's not explicitly there. So let's take a
look.
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: הכל חייבין בתקיעת שופר. Hakol chayavin bitkias shofar.
Everybody's obligated. כהנים ולויים וישראלים, גרים ועבדים משוחררים. Kohanim, Levi'im, v'Yisraelim, geirim,
va'avadim meshuchrarim. So, כהנים, לויים, ישראלים, Kohanim, Levi'im, Yisraelim, all different sort
of levels of society, converts, and freed slaves. וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס, V'tumtum v'androgynous,
and
a טומטום tumtum is somebody whose genitalia are covered up so you
don't know whether he's male or female, and an אנדרוגינוס androgynous is
someone who has both male and female primary genitalia. ומי שחציו עבד
וחציו בן חורין, U'mi shechetzyo eved v'chetzyo ben chorin, and somebody that's
half slave and half free, because all of these, there's an element
of them, right, the טומטום tumtum might be male. I mean, this
as opposed to what תוספות Tosafos said is going to assume as
we'll see in a minute that a female is exempt, but a
טומטום tumtum might be a male, an אנדרוגינוס androgynous also might הלכתית
halachikly be categorized as a male, and even somebody half free and
half slave has a part of him which is a free person
which is obligated. טומטום אינו מוציא לא את מינו ולא את שאינו
מינו. Tumtum eino motzi lo es mino v'lo es she'eino mino. A
טומטום tumtum cannot blow the שופר shofar for someone just like him,
for another טומטום, tumtum, and not for someone who's not like him,
meaning somebody who clearly is a male. Why can't a טומטום tumtum
blow for another טומטום? tumtum? Because the one who's blowing might be
a female and the one who's listening might be a male, and
therefore it will not work. אנדרוגינוס מוציא את מינו ולא את שאינו
מינו. Androgynous motzi es mino v'lo es she'eino mino. An אנדרוגינוס androgynous
can blow the שופר shofar for another אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, but not for
a non-אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, meaning a male. Why? Because אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, there are
three possibilities of how to classify an אנדרוגינוס. androgynous. What are the
three possibilities?
Male, female, and other.
Male, female, and other. So if he's male, but that's not about
this individual person. A טומטום, tumtum, his genitalia is covered up, but
what exactly a טומטום tumtum is, is different from person to person.
It depends what his physical reality is, anatomical reality is. By an
אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, it's a question of classification. All אנדרוגינוסes androgynous will share
the same classification. We just have to figure out what that classification
is. So either they're all males, then he could be מוציא motzi
another one, or they're all females, so a woman isn't obligated and
in terms of like the קיום מצוה, kiyum mitzvah, a woman could
blow for a woman but not for a man. And if it's
an other, so whatever the other is, could blow, you know, this
third category, you can be מוציא motzi somebody at the same level
as yourself. So therefore, since they're all classified in the same way,
one can be מוציא motzi another, but cannot be מוציא motzi a
male. Okay, now again, by the way, back to your point, it's
implicit here that a woman isn't good, which is why we have
all these issues around טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, but even here
it's not even stated explicitly, so that is quite fascinating. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר מר, Amar mar, now let's
unpack this: הכל
חייבין בתקיעת שופר, כהנים ולויים וישראלים. Hakol chayavin bitkias shofar, Kohanim v'Levi'im
v'Yisraelim. פשיטא, Pshita, obvious. אי הני לא מיחייבי, Ei hanei lo michayvei,
if these aren't obligated, מאן מיחייב, man michayav, who else would be
obligated? You always start with assuming like the men are obligated. So
why do you have to tell me כהנים, לויים, ישראלים? Kohanim, Levi'im,
Yisraelim? Obviously it could be rhetorical flourish, but let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says.
No, כהנים איצטריכא ליה, Kohanim itztricha lei, you have to tell me
that כהנים Kohanim are obligated. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, I
would have thought since it says,
I would have thought to say, הואיל וכתיב, ho'il u'chtiv, since it
says יום תרועה יהיה לכם, Yom truah yihiyeh lachem, a day of
blasts you should have, דליתיה אלא בתקיעה אחת דחייבי יומא הוא דמיחייבי,
d'leisay ela bitkiah achas d'chaivei yoma hu d'michayvei, people that are only
have one day of blasts, יום, yom, they, for them there's a
מצוה on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. והני כהנים, V'hanei Kohanim, but these
כהנים, Kohanim, הואיל ואיתנהו בתקיעה דכל השנה, ho'il v'isnehu bitkiah d'chol hashanah,
they're involved in blasts the whole year, דכתיב, d'chtiv, ותקעתם בחצוצרות על
עולותיכם, u'skatem bachatzotzros al olosaychem, you shall blow the trumpets on your
on your burnt offerings. So there's a, you know, they do this
as a regular part of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So maybe
there's nothing that they, you know, have to do a special blast
on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah אימא... Eima... אימא לא ליחייבו, eima lo
lichayvu, maybe they should be obligated. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
that they are. Gemara says: מי דמי? mi dami? How can you
compare them? התם חצוצרות והכא שופר. hatam chatzotzerot ve-hacha shofar. There
it's a trumpet, here it's a שופר. shofar. Why would I think
just because they do trumpet blasts that that somehow gets them out
of שופר shofar blasts? אלא אצטריכא. ella itzricha. Okay, here's why you
need to tell us. סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach amina I would
have thought to say, והתנן ve-hatnan since we teach in a משנה:
mishna: שוה היובל לראש השנה לתקיעה ולברכות, shaveh ha-yovel le-rosh ha-shanah li-teki'ah
u-le-vrachot,
that remember we taught this earlier, that on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
we learn out the blasts of the שופר shofar on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah from the פסוקים pesukim about blasting the שופר shofar on
the יובל. yovel. And therefore we have the same number of blasts
and the same type of blasts on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. and
on יובל, yovel, the same ברכות brachot and so on. But the
key here is we learn שופר shofar blasts from יובל. yovel. Okay,
מאן דאיתיה במצות יובל איתיה במצות ראש השנה. man de-isay be-mitzvah de-yovel
isay be-mitzvah de-rosh ha-shanah. If you're in the מצוה of יובל, yovel,
you're in the מצוה of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. והני כהנים, ve-hanei
Kohanim, these כהנים, Kohanim, הוה ליתנהו במצות יובל, hava leisnehu be-mitzvot yovel,
they're not fully in the יובל yovel הלכות. halachot. דתנן. de-tnan. Now,
so I'll just end the thought and then we'll unpack how they're
not the יובל yovel הלכות. halachot. I would have thought that since
כהנים Kohanim there's some יובל yovel הלכות halachot relating to land that
don't apply to כהנים Kohanim as we're about to speak. So if
they're not fully part of יובל, yovel, maybe therefore they're not fully,
you know, they're not obligated in the תקיעת שופר teki'as shofar of
יובל yovel and if they're not obligated in the תקיעת שופר teki'as
shofar of יובל yovel they're not obligated in the תקיעת שופר teki'as
shofar of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So that's why I might have
thought to exempt them. Of course it's a little funny why because
they don't have some of the מצוות of land would that get
them out of the תקיעת שופר teki'as shofar even of יובל yovel
let alone of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, But that's the structure of
the argument. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. דתנן, de-tnan,
we talk in the
משנה: mishna: כהנים ולויים מוכרין לעולם וגואלין לעולם. Kohanim ve-Levi'im mocherin le-olam
ve-go'alin le-olam. Can sell it all times and redeem it all times.
Now, what does that mean they can sell all times and redeem
it all times? Because the basic הלכה halachah is the following is
that, you know, if you sell a house from a walled city...
okay,
so here if you sell a plot of land, okay, you cannot
buy it back for two years. You cannot buy it back. You
can only start to be גואל go'el it, redeem it after, you
know, after two years has passed. The opposite is true if you
sell a house. Okay, here's your house, okay, so the first year
you can be גואל. go'el. You can only redeem it the first
year. Afterwards you cannot. Okay, so that's a normal הלכה. halachah.
כהנים Kohanim are מוכרין לעולם, mocherin le-olam, מוכרין לעולם mocherin le-olam isn't
relevant, but they are גואלין לעולם. go'alin le-olam. They can redeem it
within the first two years, they don't have that restriction, okay, and
they can also גואל לעולם, go'el le-olam, they can redeem the house
after the first year. They don't have that restriction.
Everybody else has various restrictions.
You have to wait year two years and here you only have
one year to do it. Now that's not really relevant to the
laws of the יובל, yovel, I mean to some degree it's linked
but it's not so relevant. So רש"י, Rashi so תוספות Tosafos prefers
a גירסא, girsa, רש"י Rashi has both גירסאות, girsos,
of מקדישים לעולם וגואלים לעולם. makdishim le-olam ve-go'alin le-olam. What does מקדישים
לעולם... makdishim le-olam... מקדישין לעולם makdishin le-olam or
מקדישים לעולם makdishim le-olam mean? If you sanctify your field, okay, and
you don't redeem it by the time the יובל yovel runs the
comes about, what happens to the field? Anybody know? It's a פסוק.
pasuk. לוקח? Loke'ach? No, what? It goes to the כהנים, Kohanim, excellent.
So if you don't redeem your field by the time of the
יובל yovel the field goes to the כהנים. Kohanim. If however you're
a לוי Levi or a כהן and you didn't redeem your field,
you still even after the יובל yovel you still have an option
to redeem it. So that's גואלים לעולם go'alin le-olam in the הקדש
hekdesh case. There really you're exempt from the יובל yovel laws. The
יובל yovel for a normal person would have assigned that field to
the כהנים, Kohanim, for you, you are still have the right to
buy it back even after. So you're exempt from that aspect of
the יובל yovel laws. So since they have that exemption, I would
have thought, let's keep on reading, אימא במצות ראש השנה לא ליחייבו,
eima be-mitzvah de-rosh ha-shanah lo lichayvu, maybe they wouldn't be obligated in
the מצוה of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah very funny thing to go
from that little exemption. Anyway, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan not
that way because that's a tiny little exemption and it doesn't have
those implications. Bottom line is we don't learn too much from כהנים
לויים ישראלים Kohanim, Levi'im, Yisraelim probably is more of a rhetorical flourish.
Yes.
לעולם le-olam sometimes refers to until יובל. yovel.
Yeah, in the פסוקים, pesukim, not here, here it contrasts יובל. yovel.
But that's a good point. מי שחציו בן חורין וחציו עבד אינו
מוציא לא את מינו ולא את שאינו מינו. mi she-chetzyo ben chorin
ve-chetzyo eved eino motzi lo et mino ve-lo et she-eino mino. Okay.
That's the half-and-half, you cannot be מוציא motzi your fellow slave, your
fellow person that's half-and-half, and certainly not a, you know, a normal
free male. Okay. Now,
why can't I be מוציא motzi somebody that's half-and-half if I'm half-and-half?
Because part of my שופר shofar blow is not a full תקיעה
teki'ah of מצוה. It's a תקיעה teki'ah that was generated by a
person that's half a בר חיובא bar chiyuva and half not. So
it's not a it's a sort of it's gray, it's not you
know, it's not a full תקיעת מצוה. teki'as mitzvah. And you, even
if you're half-and-half, but the part of you that's a בר חיובא,
bar chiyuva, it's funny what that means the part of you, but
anyway, but the... but you need to hear a full תקיעת מצוה.
Tkias Mitzvah. And this is a, this is a, a not full
תקיעת מצוה. Tkias Mitzvah. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, לעצמו
מוציא, Le'atzmo motzi, you could be מוציא motzi yourself. So אמר ליה
רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
back to רב הונא, Rav Huna, רב הונא, Rav Huna, מאי שנא
לכם דלא? Mai shna lachem dlo?
Why can't the half-and-half be מוציא motzi another half-and-half? דלא אתי צד
עבדות ומפקי צד חירות? Dlo ati tzad avdus u'mafki tzad cheirus?
The part of that תקיעה Tkiyah or of the person that is
a slave cannot be מוציא motzi the part of the other person
that is a free person. לעצמו נמי לא! Le'atzmo nami lo! לעצמו
נמי! Le'atzmo nami! So the same would be true even if you
want to be יוצא yotzei with your own תקיעה. Tkiyah. לא אתי
צד עבדות דידיה ומפקי צד חירות דידיה. Lo ati tzad avdus didey
u'mafki tzad cheirus didey.
So you're still generating a תקיעה Tkiyah which is half good and
half not good. So the part of your, the part of you
that is an עבד eved cannot create a תקיעה Tkiyah to be
מוציא motzi the part of you that is a free person. אלא
אמר רב נחמן, Ella amar Rav Nachman, אף לעצמו אינו מוציא. af
le'atzmo eino motzi. You're not even מוציא motzi yourself. תניא נמי הכי,
Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין
אף לעצמו אינו מוציא. Mi shechetzyo eved vechetzyo ben chorin af le'atzmo
eino motzi. Okay, so that's like a fascinating discussion of what the
גמרא Gemara imagines this guy's half and half and so on. I
have to tell you that the מנחת חינוך, Minchas Chinuch, who's like,
wrote this, you know, extensive commentary on the ספר החינוך, Sefer HaChinuch,
and it's great because he has all these interesting like questions and
he raises all these interesting hypotheticals and he tries to discuss the
exact parameters of the מצוה. He like is in love with חצי
עבד וחצי בן חורין. chatzi eved vechatzi ben chorin. Like every single
מצוה he says, what would be the הלכה halacha in this case
of a חצי עבד וחצי בן חורין chatzi eved vechatzi ben chorin
would do it, you know? It's like so trying to sort of
figure out this weird case, this mixture. It also reminds me of
this story since we're also talking about like an אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, you
know, this, this ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva comes into a, visiting a
ישיבה, yeshiva, he says, what has everyone learned? He says, we're learning
קידושין. Kiddushin. So he says, okay, can an אנדרוגינוס androgynos be מקדש
mekadesh himself? So everybody, everybody's thinking, I don't know, is there a
מעשה נתינה maaseh nesina because you're just, you know, you're giving it
to yourself? Is that really an act of קידושין? Kiddushin? And then
he says, of course not. He's his
sister! Alright, so there's your like, one of your half and half
types of things. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תני אבא בריה דרב זירא, Tni Abba brei deRav Zeira,
כל הברכות כולן, kol habrachos kulan, all of the blessings, אף על
פי שיצא מוציא. af al pi sheyatza motzi. Here we go, you
can be מוציא motzi somebody in a ברכה bracha even though you
also fulfilled your obligation. Okay, so let's say a good example would
be like, you know, a case where a ברכה bracha is actually
a מצוה, like, like a ברכה bracha of, let's say, of קידוש
Kiddush for example.
חוץ מברכת הלחם וברכת היין, chutz mibirchas halechem u'birchas hayayin, except for
like ברכת הנהנין, birchas ha'nehenin, המוציא, Hamotzi, בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri
HaGafen. ואם לא יצא מוציא. ve'im lo yatza motzi. If you haven't
made your own ברכת הנהנין, birchas ha'nehenin, then you could make it
and be יוצא yotzei for yourself and for somebody else. ואם יצא,
ve'im yatza, but if you've already made your ברכה bracha of המוציא,
Hamotzi, אינו מוציא. eino motzi. You cannot מוציא. motzi. Anyway, you've made
your בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen, you can't make it again
for someone else. A ברכת הנהנין birchas ha'nehenin starts with the fact
that it's not a מצוה that you're doing for somebody, but it's
something that is coming to relate to the food you're about to
benefit from. And if that's not a reality for you, then you
cannot, you know, just do it for the sake of somebody else.
Okay, by a מצוה, you know, I'm helping you do a מצוה.
And that's how we frame it. So it's not like I'm making
a blessing or whatever, no, I'm helping, you know, that I somehow
am not entitled to make. No, I'm helping you, I'm making the
blessing for you. But a ברכת הנהנין birchas ha'nehenin is rooted in
my deriving benefit. Me, the one who's saying it, have to actually
be deriving benefit. So I cannot do it for you if I'm
not deriving benefit. So the גמרא Gemara says, בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava,
so now we have a question. What about when ברכת הנהנין birchas
ha'nehenin becomes part of a ברכת המצוה? birchas hamitzvah? Okay, ברכת הלחם
של מצה. Birchas halechem shel matzah. So
המוציא לחם מן הארץ Hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz that you make on
מצה, matzah, okay? וברכת היין של קידוש היום, u'birchas hayayin shel kiddush
hayom, and בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen that you make on
קידוש. Kiddush. מהו? Mahu? What do we say? Do we say כיון
דחובה הוא, keivan dechovah hu, since you have to eat מצה matzah
and you have to make קידוש, Kiddush, מפיק, mapik, so therefore I
can make it for you? So I've already made קידוש Kiddush for
myself, and you come in and you say, make קידוש Kiddush for
me, right? So can I say, you know, בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri HaGafen together with the, you know, מקדש השבת? Mekadesh HaShabbat? Or
do we say, on the one hand, the whole קידוש Kiddush is
an obligation, so I'm really making, doing the מצוה ברכה bracha for
you. או דלמא ברכה לאו חובה היא. O dilma bracha lav chovah
hi. The ברכת הנהנין birchas ha'nehenin part is not an obligation. Now
what does it mean the ברכת הנהנין birchas ha'nehenin part is not
an obligation? רש"י just says in general ברכת הנהנין birchas ha'nehenin is
not an obligation, meaning if we don't frame it as a מצוה,
we say when you want to derive benefit. And it's anchored in
the reality of deriving benefit. So even therefore when it's attached to
this ברכה, bracha, it's not like you're doing a מצוה for somebody
when you do it, no, it's still fundamentally is a ברכת הנהנין.
birchas ha'nehenin. You could say it a little sharper, which is, and
this will shock you, you could make קידוש Kiddush without saying בורא
פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen, and without saying המוציא לחם מן הארץ.
Hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz. I don't mean you could make it on
bread. How? Let's say you're drinking wine before it gets dark, okay?
And then it becomes dark, and it becomes שבת, Shabbos, like this
happens sometimes when פורים Purim is on a Friday. Okay. Right, so
you're drinking wine, you made a בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen,
so the הלכה halacha is, if you remember from פסחים, Pesachim, פורס
מפה ומקדש, pores mapah umekadesh, so you put a cloth over the
המוציא Hamotzi of the bread and you say קידוש. Kiddush. You know
where your קידוש Kiddush starts with? It doesn't start with בורא פרי
הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. It starts with אשר בחר בנו, Asher Bachar
Banu,
whatever the ברכה bracha is.
Anyway, it starts with the second ברכה bracha because you don't need
a ברכת הנהנין birchas hanehenin because you've already made a בורא פרי
הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, right? Similarly, let's say, I don't know, you'd
have to think of what the scenario is because you're not allowed
to eat מצה matzah erev פסח, Pesach, you know, after, you know,
whatever, but in theory, if you had already made a המוציא, Hamotzi,
let's say, let's say for example the גמרא Gemara. talks about, you
know, מצה matzah that was made by like non-Jews and so on
that you don't use to be יוצא yotzei your מצוה with. Let's
say you'd already made a המוציא Hamotzi on that מצה. matzah. So
when you got up to eating מצה, matzah, you wouldn't have to
say המוציא. Hamotzi. You would just say על אכילת מצה. Al Achilas
Matzah. So even the ברכה bracha there is not technically necessary for
that מצוה. It's just necessary because you're deriving benefit, but in theory,
if you've already made the ברכת הנהנין, birchas hanehenin, you wouldn't even
need it as part of קידוש. Kiddush. Right? So that's, so you
understand that, right? That's, for us that's like shocking. We assume no,
קידוש Kiddush starts with בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. No, but
the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen is just because you're going
to drink. If you had a way that you had made בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen before you wouldn't need it as part
of your קידוש. Kiddush.
Right. So yeah. Rabbi, could you go, how did you read that
last line in the previous עמוד of דאורייתא? d'Oraisa? כל הברכות כולן
אף על פי שיצא,
Kol habrachos kulan
af al pi
sheyatzah,
even
if you've already made the ברכה bracha for yourself,
אף על פי שיצא, af al pi sheyatzah,
you can be מוציא motzi somebody else. So you already said קידוש,
Kiddush, you can make קידוש Kiddush for somebody else. Okay. Alright. Okay.
So anyway, but what do you do about ברכת הנהנין birchas hanehenin
that's incorporated into a מצוה? What do we say? תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear. דאמר רב אשי, D'amar Rav Ashi, כי הוינן
בי רב פפא, ki havainan bei Rav Pappa, when I was in
the house of רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הוה מקדש לן, hava mekadesh
lan, he would make קידוש Kiddush for us. וכי הוי אתי אריסיה
מדברא, vechi hava ati ariseih midabra, and when his sharecropper came from
the field, הוה מקדש ליה, hava mekadesh lei, he'd make קידוש Kiddush
for him. Now, how do you know, maybe he just made, he
maybe he started after בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. But since
he didn't distinguish, right, and presumably maybe also the sharecropper wanted to
drink from the wine, so the sharecropper needed here בורא פרי הגפן,
Borei Pri Hagafen, so we're assuming it means that he made even
the בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. So we actually say that
it does become incorporated in and you can even say the בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen for someone else after you've made קידוש,
Kiddush, and that's what we do. Okay.
By the way, making קידוש Kiddush multiple times.
Yeah, exactly. But even the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen part,
even though normally that's a ברכת הנהנין. birchas hanehenin. By the way,
I'll tell you an interesting, what do you call it, an interesting
הלכה, halacha, which is when you're making like the בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri Hagafen if you're a מסדר קידושין mesader kiddushin before the
ברכת אירוסין, birchas eirusin, right? Or even the ברכת נישואין birchas nisuin
but then it's normally someone else who's making the בורא פרי הגפן.
Borei Pri Hagafen. Because there the גמרא Gemara never mentions that the
ברכת אירוסין birchas eirusin is done on wine. It's a later מנהג,
minhag, and actually the הלכה halacha is if you don't have wine
you just go ahead and do it anyway. It's a later, it's
a גאוני Geonic מנהג, minhag, but it's a later מנהג. minhag. So
here if I'm making בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, here's another
question. When I make בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen for you,
I've already made קידוש, Kiddush, I'm making בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri
Hagafen for you now because and you know and the second ברכה,
bracha, then you don't need to, then I don't need to drink
because that's the whole point, because it's being framed as a ברכת
המצוה, birchas hamitzvah, that's why I'm allowed to make it, so I
don't need to drink. But if you're having the ברכת אירוסין birchas
eirusin and I'm saying בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, then if
that's a later addition to the ברכת אירוסין, birchas eirusin, it was
never packaged together, how could I be making a ברכת הנהנין birchas
hanehenin without getting הנאה? So a trick that מסדרי קידושין mesadrei kiddushin
do that are aware of this problem, I mean it's debated, some
want to say in the end it does get incorporated, but anyway
is that you get a little wine on your fingers and then
after you hand the cup over to the groom then you just
like lick your finger. So, but that's but when it gets packaged.
Now by the way also not to be confused is the בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen we make שבת Shabbos day. If you
make בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen and then someone comes and
says oh I didn't hear קידוש, Kiddush, could you make קידוש Kiddush
for me? בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen in שבת Shabbos day
is really totally just ברכת הנהנין. birchas hanehenin. The קידוש Kiddush on
שבת Shabbos day is really because there's an idea to have your
סעודה seuda with wine. So therefore there's no like מצוה aspect of
saying that ברכה, bracha, I mean there's a מצוה of קידוש Kiddush
as opposed to Friday night. So you cannot make a בורא פרי
הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen for someone if you've already made it for
yourself on שבת Shabbos day. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis
taught. What? תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Yeah I know.
לא יפרוס אדם פרוסה לאורחין אלא אם כן אוכל עמהם. Lo yifros
adam prusah le'orchin ela im kein ochel imahem. So don't break bread
for the guests unless you're eating with them, which means don't be
the one that's making the ברכה bracha המוציא, Hamotzi, here's a straight
ברכת הנהנין, birchas hanehenin, unless you're also getting benefit. אבל פורס הוא
לבניו ולבני ביתו כדי לחנכם במצוות. Aval pores hu levanav ulevnei beiso
kedei lechancham bemitzvot. But you can make המוציא Hamotzi for your kids
and members of your household, which might mean your wife, in order
to train them in מצוות. So you can make a ברכה bracha
even if you're not being יוצא yotzei and even a ברכת הנהנין
birchas hanehenin if it's done for the sake of חינוך. chinuch. Very
important, right? So there you are, you're trying to train your kid
to דאוון daven or whatever, can you be saying the ברכות brachos
or do you have to say ברוך אתה השם Baruch Atah Hashem
every time? You say ברוך אתה השם Baruch Atah Hashem it doesn't
exactly help him or her learn the ברכה bracha that they have
to learn. So for the sake of חינוך. chinuch. You can say
the ברכה Bracha full even if you're not
being יוצא Yotze yourself or it's not in the category of יצא
מוציא Yotza Motzi and so on. It's a ברכת הנהנין Birchas Ha'nehenin
etcetera. ובמהללו ובמגילה אף על פי שיצא מוציא. U've'hallelu u've'megilla af al
pi she'yotza motzi. But הלל Hallel and מגילה, Megilla, which are those
things, even though, you know, even if you said it once, you
can do it again and be מוציא Motzi somebody and you can
make the ברכה Bracha again for someone by those. Even though you've
read the מגילה, Megilla, you can go ahead and make the ברכה
Bracha again for a person. We normally say to the person, if
they're able to, you make the ברכה Bracha yourself, I'll read the
מגילה, Megilla, but if they're not able to, you go ahead and
you make the ברכה Bracha and we say אף על פי שיצא
מוציא. Af al pi she'yotza motzi. Yes?
Yes, on שבת Shabbos morning, if somebody makes קידוש Kiddush at שול
Shul and then they go home and they have guests, will they
say it again?
Yeah, but that's because you wanted to... so that's a good point,
I should clarify. I meant you're still sitting at the same meal
and somebody comes. Then you can't. But if you go home, the
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen you made in שול Shul doesn't
count if you want to drink wine now that you're home. It's
a... meaning even if you just wanted to drink wine, you'd have
to make another בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri HaGafen. So that's why
you make it again when you go home. Right. Yeah, that's important
point to clarify. I meant you're sitting at your meal, you made
בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen, and then somebody new comes over.
Like technically, like you make the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen
at קידוש Kiddush and have קידוש, Kiddush, you make a ברכה אחרונה,
Bracha Achrona, that meal's over, you go home, you make another one.
Right, precisely. Okay, let's move on. יום טוב של ראש השנה שחל
להיות בשבת. Yom Tov shel Rosh Hashanah she'chal lihyot b'Shabbos. Fourth and
final פרק. יום טוב של ראש השנה שחל להיות בשבת. Yom Tov
shel Rosh Hashanah she'chal lihyot b'Shabbos. The יום טוב Yom Tov of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah falls out on שבת. Shabbos. Now, by the
way, why did it have to say, I have to just comment
on this, יום טוב של ראש השנה? Yom Tov shel Rosh Hashanah?
Why didn't it just say ראש השנה שחל להיות בשבת? Rosh Hashanah
she'chal lihyot b'Shabbos? Like if you're talking about סוכות or פסח, Pesach,
you have to say יום טוב Yom Tov to distinguish it from
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. But ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, is only a
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why didn't it just say ראש השנה שחל
להיות בשבת? Rosh Hashanah she'chal lihyot b'Shabbos? So it could just be
that it is just using a parallel language that it would use
by ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah by סוכות and פסח, Pesach, and it
really doesn't mean anything. But I also think it's possible that it
is alluding back to the first משנה. Mishna. There are four ראש
השנהs. Rosh Hashanah. ארבעה ראשי שנים הם. Arba'ah rashei shanim hem. So
we're not talking about those other ones. We're talking about the יום
טוב של ראש השנה. Yom Tov shel Rosh Hashanah. But again I
want to point out how much this מסכת Masechet has managed to,
and I don't know what the explanation of this is, but in
my mind, downplay the central importance of like ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah
It starts off by saying ארבעה ראשי שנים הם. Arba'ah rashei shanim
hem. Doesn't give any like big focus on the fact that this
is a יום טוב, Yom Tov, you know? It's just, okay, it's
ראש השנה לשמיטין וליובלות Rosh Hashanah l'shmitin u'l'yovelos or whatever, doesn't sort
of... you don't get a sense it's a יום טוב. Yom Tov.
The next משנה Mishna doesn't say on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, is
a יום הדין. Yom HaDin. No. You know, ארבעה פרקים בשנה העולם
נידון. Arba'ah perakim bashana ha'olam nidon. You know, this is one of
four times. But again, you don't get a sense it's a יום
טוב. Yom Tov. It's just one of four times you're נידון. nidon.
Then we get into a whole thing about קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh
which starts in the middle of the first פרק, goes through the
second, even gets into the third. So קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh completely
spreads its tentacles out and dominates. Even the third פרק, which is
wherein it finally is talking about ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah starts with
קידוש החודש. Kiddush HaChodesh. Then you get to the משנה Mishna by
שופר, Shofar, and it doesn't even mention ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah again.
It just says, you know, כל השופרות כשרים. Kol hashofaros kesherin. So
the first like real focus on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah as a
יום טוב Yom Tov is like this משנה. Mishna. So I don't
know what to make of it exactly, but it's pretty amazing how
much, you know, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, as a יום טוב Yom
Tov is sort of downplayed in this מסכת. Masechet. Okay, so the
first mention that you have that you blow the שופר Shofar on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. by the way, was in passing in the
משנה Mishna in the previous משנה. Mishna. It said, you know, it
says like this, שופר של ראש השנה של יעל פשוט ופיו מצופה
זהב Shofar shel Rosh Hashanah shel yael pashut u'piv metzupeh zahav etcetera.
Right? So it took a long time until we start sort of
focusing on it. It's related to the idea that the תורה Torah
never calls this ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah Right! But you would דווקא
davka think that that's where חז"ל Chazal might want to heighten its
role as such, you know, to give it that identity that we
have now given it. So again, I do... but I agree, I
think that that's fascinating. Okay. So now it says like this. יום
טוב של ראש השנה שחל להיות בשבת. Yom Tov shel Rosh Hashanah
she'chal lihyot b'Shabbos. So the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah falls out on
שבת. Shabbos. במקדש היו תוקעים, Ba'Mikdash hayu tokin, they'd still blow the
שופר Shofar in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, אבל לא במדינה, aval
lo ba'medina, not outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. What did outside
mean?
It could either mean outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash proper, even
in ירושלים Yerushalayim they wouldn't blow, although later it's going to sound
like... it's going to say they did blow in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so
let's interpret it to mean that outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim they would
not blow. משחרב בית המקדש, Mishe'charav Beis HaMikdash, once the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash was destroyed, התקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי,
hiskin Rabban Yochanan ben Zakai, Rabban יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakai
established, יהיו תוקעין בכל מקום שיש בו בית דין. yihyu tokin b'chol
makom she'yesh bo Beis Din. They wouldn't only do it in the...
or they wouldn't do it in the מקדש Mikdash because there was
no מקדש, Mikdash, but nevertheless they would continue the practice wherever there
was a בית דין. Beis Din. Now, often we are inclined to
say that that's like זכר למקדש, zecher l'Mikdash, right? To remember what
they did in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we'll continue it in
a בית דין. Beis Din. But notice that the משנה Mishna does
not say זכר למקדש. zecher l'Mikdash. Okay? He's continuing the practice without
a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's not necessarily being framed as זכר
למקדש, zecher l'Mikdash, and we're going to revisit that when we get
to the story in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So אמר רבי אלעזר,
Amar Rabi Elazar, Rabbi אלעזר Elazar says, לא התקין רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי אלא ביבנה בלבד. lo hiskin Rabban Yochanan ben Zakai ela be'Yavne
bilvad. No, no, no. He didn't do it in any בית דין.
Beis Din. I mean, that would be all over. He only did
it in יבנה, Yavne, which was like the central בית דין. Beis
Din. and where the center of Judaism moved after the חורבן הבית.
Churban Habayis. So אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him,
אחד יבנה ואחד כל מקום שיש בו בית דין, echad Yavne v'echad
kol makom sheyesh bo Beis Din, whether יבנה Yavne or any place
that there was a בית דין. Beis Din. So ועוד זאת הייתה
ירושלים יתירה על יבנה, ve'od zos hayisa Yerushalayim yesira al Yavne, and
then additionally ירושלים Yerushalayim was greater than יבנה Yavne in the following
way. Now what do you mean additionally? So far we're saying it's
the same, right? יבנה Yavne they would blow, everybody agrees יבנה Yavne
they would blow and they'd blow in ירושלים Yerushalayim on שבת. Shabbos.
So the גמרא Gemara. will discuss what the ועוד ve'od means. But
anyway, in the following way ירושלים Yerushalayim was greater than יבנה, Yavne,
שכל עיר שהיא רואה ושומעת וקרובה ויכולה לבוא, shekol ir shehi ro'eh
v'shome'a v'krova v'yekhola lavo, any city that was in the environs of
ירושלים Yerushalayim that could see ירושלים Yerushalayim and could hear, and you
hear the שופר shofar blowing all the way from outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
and was close enough that they could come from the neighboring city,
they would blow in those cities as well. וביבנה לא היו תוקעין
אלא בבית דין בלבד, uv'Yavne lo hayu toke'in ela b'veis din bilvad,
and in יבנה Yavne they would only do it in the immediate
presence of the בית דין. Beis Din. So even if they continued
it in יבנה Yavne and maybe in other בתי דין, battei din,
it would not be the same as ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ירושלים Yerushalayim it
sort of reached out to all of the environs would allow it
to be blown on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara So we don't even know why there's a problem
of blowing it on שבת. Shabbos. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara
מנא הני מילי? manan hanei milei? Where do you get this idea
from that there should be a problem of blowing the שופר shofar
on שבת? Shabbos? אמר לוי בר לחמא אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא,
Amar Levi bar Lachma amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina, כתוב אחד אומר
kasuv echad omer שבתון זכרון תרועה, Shabbason zichron teruah, a day of
rest, a remembrance of blast. So obviously it can mean blasts are
for a remembrance of us to God, but here the גמרא's going
to
read it as it's a day that we remember the blasts but
we don't hear the blasts. וכתוב אחד אומר v'kasuv echad omer יום
תרועה yom teruah יהיה לכם, yihyeh lakhem, a day of actual blasts
יהיה לכם. yihyeh lakhem. לא קשיא, lo kashya, how do you reconcile
it? It's not difficult. כאן ביום טוב שחל להיות בשבת כאן ביום
טוב שחל להיות בחול, kan b'yom tov she'chal lihyos b'Shabbos kan b'yom
tov she'chal lihyos b'chol, it depends whether it's on a weekday or
on שבת. Shabbos. On שבת Shabbos it's only a remembrance of the
blasts and that's why. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רבא says back, אם
מדאורייתא, im mid'Oraisa, if really biblically you're not supposed to blow the
שופר shofar on שבת, Shabbos, אי במקדש היכי תקנינן? hi bamikedash heichi
takinan? How do we blow it in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
Clearly if we're doing it in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's some Rabbinic problem that we're waiving
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Because if it's a biblical issue,
even if it's not let's say a violation of שבת Shabbos or
יום טוב, Yom Tov, but if it's a biblical idea not to
blow, then we shouldn't be blowing in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
either. ועוד, V'od, הלאו מלאכה היא? halav melakha hi? And number two,
why should it be a problem blowing a שופר shofar in terms
of a violation problem? It's not a מלאכה. melakha. דצריך קרא למעוטי?
d'tsarikh kra l'mautei? That you would need a verse to prohibit it?
דתנא דבי שמואל, d'tana d'vei Shmuel, as the school of שמואל Shmuel
teaches, כל מלאכת עבודה לא תעשו, kol melekhes avoda lo ta'asu, do
not do any מלאכה melakha of labor. But it's מלאכה, melakha, יצא
תקיעת שופר ורדיית הפת, yatza tki'as shofar u'ridiyas hapas, it excludes blowing
of a שופר shofar and peeling the bread that's been cooking off
of the sides of the oven. שהיא חכמה ואינה מלאכה, shehi chokhma
v'eina melakha, it's a skill, it's a highly technical professional skill, but
it does not actually fall in the category of a מלאכה, melakha,
it is not actually a creative labor. So therefore if it's not
prohibited, why would we not be able to do it on שבת?
Shabbos? אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא says, מדאורייתא מישרא
שרי, mid'Oraisa mishra sharei, biblically you really could blow שופר shofar on
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah on שבת. Shabbos. ורבנן הוא דגזרו ביה, v'rabanan
hu d'gazru bei, and the Rabbis made
a גזירה, gzera, דאמר רבה, d'amar Raba, like רבה Raba says, דאמר
רבה, d'amar Raba, the same statement of רבה Raba to explain multiple
places we see that you would not do things on שבת, Shabbos,
שופר, shofar, לולב, and מגילה. megilla. רבה Raba says, הכל חייבין בתקיעת
שופר ואין הכל בקיאין בתקיעת שופר, hakol hayavu b'tki'as shofar v'ein hakol
b'ki'im b'tki'as shofar, everybody's obligated but it's not so easy to blow
the שופר, shofar, not everybody knows how
to do it. ואם יטלנו בידו וילך אצל בקי ללמוד, v'im yitlenu
b'yado v'yeilekh etzel baki lilmod, ויעבירנו ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים, v'ya'avirenu arba
amos b'rashus harabim, you would take your שופר shofar and you'd go
carry it to somebody who knows how to do it, and you
would forget the fact that it's שבת Shabbos and you'd wind up
carrying it ארבע אמות arba amos in רשות הרבים reshus harabim and
violate
שבת. Shabbos. והיינו טעמא דלולב והיינו טעמא דמגילה, v'hainu ta'ama d'lulav v'hainu
ta'ama d'megilla, that's the same reason why you don't do לולב on
שבת Shabbos and you don't do מגילה megilla on שבת, Shabbos, we're
afraid it's going to lead to carrying. And we don't have that
concern in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because as we know, we
often do not have certain rabbinic concerns in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Two points about this and then we'll pick up with this
tomorrow. But two final points is number one is the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
does not reject this reason that the גמרא started with. The ירושלמי
Yerushalmi seems to understand that it really is biblical that there's a
different status of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah on שבת Shabbos than ראש
השנה during the week. That's point number one, that it actually dives
into that biblical distinction.
And point number two
is I forgot what I was going to say now.
What was I going to say?
I don't know. Okay, so we'll end with that and pick up
tomorrow. Yes.